I think of all the stories that we've investigated
so far, all the fundamental myths of creation
that we've investigated so far, the two that
we're going to talk about in detail today
are probably the two stories that have had
more impact on the course of world history
than any other two.
I'm going to talk in some detail today about
the story of creation laid out in Genesis
and also the story of the Buddha's enlightenment.
Both stories are also characterized by a kind
of depth that's virtually elimitless.
And I think in some ways that the topics we're
going to discuss today are the most enlightening
of all the many ideas that we've traveled
through so far in this series.
So, we're gonna be concentrating on an analysis
of this schema again.
The idea being here of course that the world
of experience, which is the world that mythology
is attempting to describe has these fundamental
constituent elements, one associated with
chaos or nature or the unknown, one associated
with culture or the great father or the predictable.
And another associated with the archetypical
son, the individual who's the offspring of
the interplay of these two fundamental forces
But given that part of the purpose of this
series is to elucidate the causes of war and
motivation for war, attention paid to the
dualistic nature of the individual is of,
of paramount importance.
So we could say that just as nature has it's
terrible side and just as culture has its
terrible side, so the individual has his or
her terrible side.
And the depth of that, capacity say for atrocity
and vengefulness is just as deep as the depth
of terror that the unknown itself holds.
I think this is a difficult, a difficult fact
for normal individuals to grasp, given that
we're highly motivated to view ourselves as,
if not precisely good, at least as relatively
harmless.
But the evidence that as individuals we are
relatively harmless is very, very thin indeed.
And I don't think it's possible to understand
the depth of motivation for atrocity and social
conflict without coming to terms with the
capacity for evil that's characteristic of
the individual.
Now both the story in Genesis and the story
of the Buddha's enlightenment, lay bare in
many ways the nature of the structure of individual
evil.
And also not only it's structure, but its
motivation.
Why it is that people would turn more or less
voluntarily away from the good and embrace
what can only be described as it's polar opposite.
So in addition to making reference to this
structural schema of course, we're also going
to be discussing it's, the typical mode of
interaction of these elements of experience.
You may note for example that this diagram
with which you're now very familiar, the notion
of order, chaos and reestablishment of order
also parallels the structure of the story
in Genesis, the creation where human beings
are created first and exist in a paradisal
state.
That that paradise is disrupted as, as a consequence
of some, some event of virtually cosmic significance,
that as a consequence of that disruption people
are destined to live a profane existence in
constant wait for the next state of order.
So just as this is a fundamental archetypical
structure so that fundamental archetypical
structure is, constitutes the, the basic grammar
for this story in Genesis.
Now what we're gonna do to begin with is to
describe precisely how this idea of paradise,
descent and the search for paradise is illustrated
symbolically in Genesis and exactly what those
symbolic representations mean.
The idea here being that the reason that the
authors of Genesis, the multiple authors of
Genesis extending over thousands and thousands
of years chose those symbols as not because
they were labouring to be obscure or not because
they were establishing a pre-empirical representation
of reality, a kind of quasi scientific representation,
but because these symbols have an elusive
or metaphorical richness that enables a story,
although short to be characterized by an almost
infinite depth.
That's part of the reason.
The other part of the reason is that when
you say something profound, you say it using
the language, the clearest language that you
have access to.
And if the story is almost unutterably profound,
then the images in which it is enshrouded
are almost incomprehensibly complex.
It has to be that way because if the target
of the investigation is reality itself, something
so complex that we cannot conceptualize it
fully, then the language that we use to represent
that reality has to stretch us to the limits
of our ability to understand
and it is the case that the story in Genesis
say as much as the stories of Buddhist enlightenment
constitutes an artistic endeavor on the part
of the human race to portray the nature of
human reality and to explain the behavioural
and philosophical consequences of that reality.
That being a tall order perhaps we should
forgive the multiple authors for only being
able to manage it in a way that's essentially
imagistic and dramatic, rather than explicit,
logical, philosophical and fully developed.
So the first thing I'd like to point out to
you is to, is a statement made by Eliade,
which I think is one of the most enlightening
things I ever read.
Now, the first thing that Eliade does is describe
the universality of flood mythology.
But then he puts a twist on it.
So the idea behind flood mythology is something
like this, if societies deviate from an emergent,
a necessarily emergent kind of morality, a
kind of morality that takes the viewpoint
of all the inhabitants of a given society
into account, if a society deviates from that
viewpoint sufficiently, it dooms itself to
annihilation.
That annihilation being represented mythologically
as the flooding of the society by the precosmogonic
waters, the primordial element or chaos.
So societies that are tyrannical doom themselves
to eradication by chaos, a simple equation.
But made more complicated by Eliade, his observation
that more than one factor plays a role in
the establishment of the tyranny.
On the one hand there's straight degeneration
of cultural presuppositions in that if you
establish a state or a game, which has particular
rules, because the environment is constantly
transforming itself, the rules by necessity
become out of date.
So merely as a consequence of the progression
of time, the presuppositions on which any
state are founded tend to become less and
less relevant to the current environment.
Okay.
So there’s this aging and senility merely
as a consequence of thermodynamic processes.
But then Iliad also points out that there's
one additional factor which has to be attributed,
not to society, but to the individuals that
make up that society, which is that the strictures
and rules on which society was founded can
be constantly and carefully updated when necessary,
If all the individuals that make up that society
are perfectly willing to confront exemplars
of emerging chaos in their own lives when
those exemplars emerge, which is to say that
it's perfectly reasonable to be guided in
your personality by the structures of your
state.
But if you face something unknown that those
rules cannot handle, it's a moral necessity
and obligation on your part to face that emergent
anomaly forthrightly to solve it if you can,
and then to communicate the consequences of
your solution to the rest of the members of
your society.
Now what Eliade points out is that the individual
who, who removes him or her self from the
responsibility of confronting their own anomaly
speeds the process by which the state decays.
So the decay of the state and the possibility
for the emergence of chaos is an interaction
between the tenancy of the state to disorder,
the tendency of the state to, archaism and
senility merely as a consequence of change
and the voluntarily the voluntary unwillingness
of the citizens that comprise that state to
face the unknown courageously when it confronts
them.
So Eliade says: that the deluge myth, deluge
myth is almost universally disseminated.
It is documented in all the continents, although
very rarely in Africa probably because of
the relative shortage of water.
And on various cultural levels.
A certain number of variants seem to be the
result of dissemination, first from Mesopotamia
and then from India.
It is equally possible that one or several
diluvial catastrophes gave rise to fabulous
narratives, but it would be risky to explain
so widespread a myth by phenomena of which
no geological traces have been found.
That majority of the flood myths seem in some
sense to form part of the cosmic rhythm.
The old world, people by a fallen humanity
is submerged under the water and sometime
later a new world emerges from the aquatic
chaos.
In a large number of variants the flood is
the result of the sins or ritual faults of
human beings.
Sometimes it results simply from the wish
of a divine being to put an end to mankind.
The chief causes lie at once therefore in
the sins of men and the decrepitude of the
world.
by the mere fact that it exists - That is,
that it lives and produces - The cosmos gradually
deteriorates and ends by falling into decay.
This is the reason why it has to be recreated.
In other words, the flood realizes on a macrocosmic
scale what is symbolically affected during
the New Year festival.
The end of the world and the end of a sinful
humanity in order to make a new creation possible.
So then the question might arise logically
enough, what is it that would motivate an
individual to work to avoid anomaly when it
emerges in his or her own life.
And to risk an eventual flood.
And even more profoundly, what would motivate
an individual perhaps to work for the antithesis
of order, to work to promote the emergence
of chaos, since we know that people are relatively
ambivalent in their moral stance
Is it possible that we can create a compelling
motivational story for the desire of the individual
as such to work against the emergence of the
good rather than for it.
So let's take a look at what Genesis says
about the creation of experience.
So first of all, remember we're taking a phenomenological
stance on this story, which is to say that
this story is not an objective retelling of,
of materialistic emergence.
It’s something more specifically dramatic.
It describes the nature of human experience.
Okay?
The nature of conscious human experience.
And in fact the creation story of Genesis
lays explicit stress on individual consciousness
literally as a precondition for being itself.
Which is to say that underlying the story
of Genesis is the notion that without whatever
consciousness is, there would be no segregated
entities and therefore no being.
So this is one manner in which Genesis attempts
to put human beings at the centre of the cosmos,
so to speak, which is the idea that the world
independently of consciousness, whatever that
world is absolutely needs to be reflected
by consciousness in order to exist in any
sense that existence could reasonably be defined.
First chapter:
"In the beginning God created the heaven and
the earth.
And the earth was without form and void.
And darkness was on the face of the deep."
Now, the idea that the earth was without form
and void takes us back to the [13:48:55] Mesopotamian
creation myth and because the word for void,
the Hebrew word for void is “Tehom”.
And “Tehom” is a word derived from Timat.
And the void, the chaos that constitutes the
unformed condition of the cosmos prior to
the elaboration of being is assimilated to
the same category as Timat, which is this
terrible unformed and frightening aprioric
condition that has to be courageously confronted
in order to manifest itself as being.
"And the earth was without form and void and
darkness was on the face of the deep."
So now you see another, another interplay
of opposites here between matter and water,
the primordial elements.
So first of all it's heaven and earth.
And then it's earth and water and, and the
height and the deep.
And the spirit of God moved upon the face
of the water.
So another opposite: that interaction between
spirit and whatever it is that the precosmogonic
water or chaos constitutes.
"And God said let there be light.
And there was light.
And God saw the light, that it was good.
And God divided the light from the darkness.
"
And then a prototypical division between light,
which is associated with illumination and
enlightenment and consciousness because we're
conscious during the day.
And the sun and life that emerges nested inside
this, the initial opening lines of this sentence.
Northrop Frye notes that there's tremendous
emphasis on the notion of a repetitive cycling
of days and nights in the opening sentences
of Genesis, even though from a formal perspective
this emphasis is paradoxical because the notion
of the day emerges before the creation of
the sun.
And Fry's point is not that this is some careless
gesture on the part of the people who authored
Genesis.
But more that it's an attempt to emphasize
the idea of a cyclical relationship between
consciousness and light and darkness and chaos
and to highlight the idea that this cyclical
relationship is somehow absolutely vital to
being itself.
So Genesis one five says "and God called the
light day and the darkness he called night.
And the evening and the morning were the first
day "
Frye says "... the central metaphor underlying
beginning is not really birth at all.
It is rather the moment of waking from sleep.
When one world disappears, a world of virtuality
and potential, and another comes into actual
being.
This is still contained within a cycle.
We know that at the end of the day we shall
return to the world of sleep..."
and that's a notion that has a metaphorical
resonance because there's the sleep that punctuates
periods of consciousness.
And then there's the great sleep at the end
of life, which is characterized by the complete
cessation of consciousness.
We know that at the end of the day we shall
return to the world of sleep.
But in the meantime there's a sense of self-transcendence
of a consciousness getting up from an unreal
into a real or at least more real world.
This sense of awakening into a greater degree
of reality is expressed by Haraclitis as a
passing from a world where everyone has his
own logos, into a world where there's a common
logos - experience that we all share.
"Genesis presents the creation as a sudden
coming into being of a world through articulate
speech, which is another aspect of logos"logos
incorporates the idea of creative exploration,
And then the formulation of the consequences
of that exploration in verbally communicable
categories
Right?
Which give our, give our aspects of our being
their defined boundaries and parameters and
enable us to establish a shared mode of social
being- through articulate speech conscious
perception light and stability.
Something like this metaphor of awakening
may be the real reason for the emphasis on
days and such recurring phrases.
"And the evening and the morning were the
first day", even before the day as we know
it was established with the creating of the
sun
The most fundamental pair of conflicting and
cyclically interacting pairs of opposites
that is portrayed in Genesis is essentially
the pairing of chaos versus order, chaos versus
generative order.
And a poem by F.I Tiuitchev expresses this
idea extremely well and very powerfully.
So I'm going to read it to you.
When sacred night sweeps heavenward she takes
the glad the winsome day.
Unfolding it,
rolls up it's golden carpet that had been
spread over an abysmal pit.
Gone vision like as the external world.
And man a homeless orphan has to face
in utter helplessness naked, alone
the blackness of immeasurable space.
Upon himself he has to lean with mind
abolished, thought unfathered in the dim
depths of his soul he sinks.
For nothing comes
from outside to support or limit him.
All life and brightness seem an ancient dream
while in the substance of the night
unraveled, alien, he now perceives
a faithful something that is his by right.
Um, absolutely brilliant poetic statement,
I think.
Laying out very nicely, very richly the, the
fundamental nature of the existential paradox
that constitutes human life.
Pointing to a very profound sense of futility
and fear.
But then beyond that to the notion that in
the depths of the unknown, in the depths of
the darkness and in the depths of all that,
that's fundamentally unfaceable, there still
lurks something that can be discovered given
sufficient courage.
Another fundamental division portrayed indirectly
in Genesis, the word versus chaos.
So what you have in genesis is an absolutely
stellar idea.
I think perhaps the most fundamental contribution
of archaic Jewish thinking to western and
world civilization, which is that although
it is easier in some ways to consider the
actual matrix of things, their material substrate
as the strata from which they emerge, it is
equally reasonable and perhaps more pragmatically
useful to note that things only exist because
of the interaction between the logos, the
word that characterizes consciousness.
And whatever this matrix is.
So in Jewish thought and then Christian thought,
and of course in thoughts of that sort echoed
throughout the world, there's the idea that
consciousness associated with the transcendent
directly associated with the deity is actually
the thing that in interaction with this matrix
give, gives rise to being.
Genesis plays a stress, places stress on this
notion of the internal logos, the individual
consciousness in two very complex ways.
It first says that it's the word of God, the
logos of God that gives, that gives order
to chaos and makes being emerge.
But then even more particularly it's the,
it’s the self-conscious logos of individual
humans, their capacity not just to see the
world as an object.
But also to see themselves as an object that
gives the world the particular value slant
that it has for us.
which is to say that not only are we in a
world where the subject and the object are
separated.
And, and therefore experience and suffer the
consequences of that separation-But even more
particularly we are the only creatures who
are so conscious that we can observe ourself
as objects.
And the consequence of that is that because
we've extended our consciousness to ourself,
we're capable of conceptualizing things that
other creatures cannot conceptualize.
Such as the infinite possibility that lays
manifest of the unknown but also the fact
that as individuals we're subject to our finite
limitations, right?
That we can become diseased.
That we can become mentally ill.
And that finally we'll die.
And so the idea here is that something like
the extension of logos to the object, to the
subject has made human existence finally problematic.
And genesis refers to this as essentially
the heritable sin of Adam.
Because we're aware of our own vulnerability
as a genetic consequence merely of being human.
There's a transformation in the nature of
experience that has essentially cosmic significance.
Lao Tzu in the Tao Te Ching makes a comment
on the formless chaos that constitutes the
matrix of things, the origin of things in
the following manner.
He says "there was something formless yet
complete that existed before heaven and earth
without sound, without substance.
"
This is the void or the chaos.
"Dependent on nothing, unchanging all pervading.
Unfailing.
One may think of it as the mother of all things
under heaven."
The idea here being that whatever experience
is in the absence of a delimited human consciousness,
is something that’s outside the boundaries
of time.
Because time -temporality is a human attribute.
And it's outside the boundaries of spatial
limitation because only human beings with
their delimited and fixed size can attribute
spatial aspects to being itself.
So whatever it is, is that exists without
us, is so comprehensive and so complete and
transcends temporal dimensions to such a great
degree that it can't be conceptualized as
being at all.
It’s something that transcends being to
such a degree that it's not even nameable
but still exists as "the mother of all things
under heaven".
Now Genesis formally associates the human
being with logos.
And this is a determinative move in human
history just as the Mesopotamians first hypothesized
that their emperor was equivalent to Marduk,
the force that confronted Timat and carved
her into pieces and made the world, and just
as the Egyptians conceptualized their pharaoh
as the intermingling between Osiris, the stability
of the state and Horus the exploratory hero.
And then disseminated that identity down the
aristocratic levels, closer and closer to
the individual, individual.
So the ancient Hebrews said, “and God said
let us make man in our image after our likeness.”
Now, it could be said that the logical derivation
of that statement is that god looks like human
beings.
Or conversely that God is an old man with
a beard.
But it means something I think that's more
sophisticated than that.
Which is that the central aspect that's associated
with this transcendent deity, the logos, which
is the thing that gives rise to order as a
consequence of it's confrontation with chaos
is also the thing that centrally characterizes
human consciousness.
And so with that there's this transcendent
notion that inside each human being is a spark
of genuine divinity.
And it’s the manifestation of that divinity
in human temporal and spatial parameters that
literally keeps the cosmos generating.
"So God created his, man in his own image
in the image of God created he, him.
Male and female created he them and let them
have dominion over the fish of the sea and
the fowl of the air and over the cattle and
over all the earth and over every creeping
thing that creepeth upon the earth.
"
Now fundamentalist Christians read this as
an injunction, right?
This is what human beings should do, dominate
all other living things.
But it's more like a description, which is
that the consequence of the embeddedness of
this spark of divinity in the individual is
precisely what gave rise to the human ability
to dominate the planet.
Which is an ability that at least at the moment
seems fundamentally unparalleled, with no
limit in sight.
So it's not an injunction so much as a cold-hearted
description.
There's a very profound idea underlying the
necessity of the creation of the individual
human being.
Here's a line of archaic Jewish speculation
that runs something like this:
Why is the creation of a limited subject necessary
if God's omniscient and omnipotent and omnipresent?
Why would he bother creating anything outside
of himself?
And the line of speculation runs like this.
The one thing that a being that is complete
in all regards even all hypothetical regards
lacks by necessity his limitation.
And as a consequence of that anything that's
absolute is not complete and can't be complete
without limitation.
And so there's an emergent idea in Genesis.
And most notions of the emergence of human
consciousness that the absolute needs the
reflection point of a delimited being to actually
spring into some kind of defined actuality.
So that being itself becomes an interplay
between the necessary limitations of the finite
and the transcendent reality of the absolute.
And so being is something that emerges because
of the fact as another ancient Jewish tradition
has it, God and man are in a sense twins,
mutually dependent on one another for their
defined being.
From such a perspective, being has the same
nature as a game.
When you're playing a game you have to play
by rules.
Which means that there are things that you
can do while playing the game.
But there are many, many things you can't
do.
And that the game could not exist without
the limitations.
Also predicated on the idea that the imposition,
the Nietzschian idea that the imposition of
limitations on a structure actually gives
rise to the possibility of diverse new forms.
Which is also a very sophisticated way of
conceptualizing the world.
So from the perspective of Genesis, the individual
is the locale of the experiential drama.
And the fact that the individual is limited
is a necessary precondition for being.